A Guide to the Petersburg State Colony Commitment Papers, 1934-1955
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Petersburg State Colony Commitment Papers, 1934-1955
The Library of Virginia
41741
1.6 cu. ft. (5 boxes)
Petersburg State Colony
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
As of September 11, 2019, medical records will be open 125 years after the date of creation or after date closed, whichever is later. The Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act (HIPAA) requires that individually identifiable health information of a decedent be protected for 50 years following the date of death of the individual (45 CFR 164.502(f)).
Protected health information (PHI) as defined under the Privacy Regulations issued under the Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act (HIPAA) includes, but is not limited to, personally identifiable information such as names, addresses, and social security numbers. Restricted material may include, but is not limited to: commitment papers. Please contact Archives Research Services for further information.
Acquisition Information
Transferred by Linda C. Coake, Southside Virginia Training Center, 26317 W. Washington St., Warehouse Building 120, Petersburg, Virginia, 23803, 14 February 2005.
Biographical/Historical Information
During the earliest years of mental health treatment in Virginia, those with mental illness and/or mental retardation were grouped together at the state hospitals. However, during the first few decades of the 20th century an effort was made to move those with mental retardation to separate facilities. In March 1938, the Virginia General Assembly authorized the establishment of a colony for African-American feeble-minded people in Petersburg. The act established the colony as a state institution separate from Central State Hospital, the state hospital specifically for black citizens. Although it was a separate institution, the colony operated on the same grounds as the hospital. Known as the Petersburg State Colony, the new facility was given land located in Prince George County (later partly in Dinwiddie County as well), and assigned the task of admitting mostly younger patients with the propensity for academic and vocational training and future employment. The colony was advised to give preference to "indigent colored children who would be most likely to receive benefit from colony care and training." This often meant that older mentally retarded people were refused treatment, as were those younger patients who showed signs of aggression or other problems that would make them difficult to train.
In 1954, the Virginia General Assembly voted to change the institution's name from the Petersburg State Colony to the Petersburg Training School and Hospital. The name was changed again in 1971 to the Southside Virginia Training Center. The facility moved from its original buildings in the early 1960s, but still remains part of the Central State Hospital campus. It continues to specialize in providing services for Virginians with various levels of mental retardation. As a side note, in 1960 the land and structures formally known as the Petersburg Training School and Hospital were transferred to the College of William and Mary for the establishment of a two-year branch campus. In 1961, Richard Bland College opened its doors to students. The original hospital buildings remained, but were converted into classrooms and offices, many of which are still in use.
Scope and Content
Contains commitment papers for applicants to Petersburg State Colony. The papers include correspondence, psychological evaluations, IQ test results, Children's Bureau reports, juvenile case records, and Department of Mental Hygiene and Hospitals interrogatories, histories and exams. The envelopes that housed the papers contain the patient's name, date of commitment, and date of admission or reason for rejection. Affixed to the papers was a label stating that these cases were "inactive," but a definition of what this means was not included. It appears that some of the committed children were offered acceptance, but whether they were actually received is unclear.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Commitment Papers, 1934-1955
Arranged chronologically by year of commitment (not admittance), and then alphabetically by patient last name within.
Commitment papers less than 125 years old are closed.
Contents List
- Series I. Commitment Papers, 1934-1955. (Box 1-5.)
  - 1934. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1936 C-F. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1936 P. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1937. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1939 A-C. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1939 S. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1940 A-B. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1940 C-D. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1940 H. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1940 J. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1940 M. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1940 R. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1940 V. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 1940 W. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1941 B-C. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 1941 D-G. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 1941 H-J. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 1941 M-R. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 1941 T. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 1941 W. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 1942 B. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 1942 B. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - 1942 C-M. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - 1942 P. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - 1942 S-T. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - 1942 W. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 1943 B. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - 1943 C-F. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - 1943 H-J. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1943 M. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 1943 P-T. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 1944 A-H. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - 1944 J-L. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 1945 B-C. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - 1945 F-J. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - 1946 A-F. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - 1946 M. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - 1946 R-W. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - 1947. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - 1948 B. (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - 1948 C. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - 1948 G-H. (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - 1948 L. (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - 1948 M. (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - 1948 M. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - 1948 P-W. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - 1949 B. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - 1949 B-C. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - 1949 D-F. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - 1949 J. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - 1949 J. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - 1949 L-R. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - 1949 S-T. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - 1949 W. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - 1950 B. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - 1950 C-G. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - 1950 R-S. (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - 1950 T. (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - 1951. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - 1952. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - 1953. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - 1954. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - 1955. (Box 5, Folder 5)